Finding Aid for Arthur Dunham Papers ca. 1900-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Community Organization
  - Subject file
    - Meetings (Box 18)
    - Methods (Box 18)
    - Michigan, University of, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - National Conference on Social Welfare (Box 18)
    - Nature (Box 18)
    - Negotiation (Box 18)
    - Neighborhood centers and organization (Box 18)
    - New Conscientious Objection (Box 18)
    - New York-SCAA (Box 18)
    - Organization (Box 18)
    - Outlook (Box 18)
    - Planning (Box 18)
    - Practice (Box 18)
    - Principles (Box 18)
    - Problem solving (Box 18)
    - Problems (Box 18)
    - Program (Box 18)
    - Public relations (Box 18)
    - Public relations-public speaking (Box 18)
    - Public welfare (Box 18)
    - Race relations (Box 18)
    - Records (Box 18)
    - Research (Box 18)
    - Research and fact-finding (Box 18)
    - Resources (Box 18)
    - Ross, Murray G. (Box 18)
    - Rural (Box 18)
    - School (Box 18)
    - Sectarian (Box 19)
    - Skills (Box 19)
    - Social action, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Social planning (Box 19)
    - Social work and social welfare (Box 19)
    - Standards (Box 19)
    - Statewide (Box 19)
    - Statevide-NASW paper (Box 19)
    - Supervision (Box 19)
    - Survey (Box 19)
    - Systems theory (Box 19)
    - Teaching materials, 9 folders (Box 19)
    - Terminology (Box 19)
    - Types of community action (Box 19)
    - United Kingdom (Box 19)
    - United Way (Box 19)
    - Warren, Roland L. (Box 19)
    - Workplans and progress reports (Box 19)
    - Worker (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
  - Courses
    - General, 6 folders (Box 19)
    - Committees (Box 19)
    - Councils and Chests (Box 19)
    - Examinations, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Field work (Box 20)
    - Fresno, Spring 1962, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Grades (Box 20)
    - Harper, etc. (Box 20)
    - Hawaii, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Manchester (Box 20)
    - Michigan, University of (Box 20)
    - Missouri, University of 1963-1964 (Box 20)
    - Missouri, University of,Columbia 1964-1965 (Box 20)
    - Missouri, University of, Kansas City 1964-1965 (Box 20)
    - Practice course, teaching notes, 5 folders (Box 20)
    - Richmond Professional Institute
      - General, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Workshop January 1967 (Box 20)
      - Workshop June 1967 (Box 20)
    - Seminar (Box 20)
    - Stephens College
      - Community leadership (Box 20)
      - Teaching materials (Box 20)
    - West Virginia 1967, 2 folders (Box 20)
- Social Welfare Administration
  The series labeled Social Welfare Administration was organized by Dunham into subseries reflecting the use which he made of these materials. The series includes a subject file subseries apparently used by Dunham for his personal reference and a course subseries with information about the courses Dunham taught in this area.
  - Subject file
    - Accounting (Box 20)
    - Agencies (Box 20)
    - Authority (Box 20)
    - Bibliography (Box 20)
    - Boards (Box 20)
    - Book, proposed (Box 20)
    - Case materials, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Centralization (Box 21)
    - Communication (Box 21)
    - Correspondence (Box 21)
    - Democracy (Box 21)
    - Dictation (Box 21)
    - Dynamics, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Employment (Box 21)
    - Evaluation (Box 21)
    - Executive, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Expert (Box 21)
    - Filing (Box 21)
    - Finance (Box 21)
    - Job description (Box 21)
    - History (Box 21)
    - Leadership (Box 21)
    - Office manuals (Box 21)
    - Organization (Box 21)
    - Personnel (Box 21)
    - Personnel-Evaluation (Box 21)
    - Policies (Box 21)
    - Principles (Box 21)
    - Records (Box 21)
    - Simplifying one's job, 4 folders (Box 21)
    - Staff (Box 21)
    - Supervision (Box 21)
    - Time study (Box 21)
    - Training (Box 21)
    - Unions (Box 21)
    - Working plan (Box 21)
    - Writing (Box 21)
    - Yardsticks (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Courses
    - Undated (Box 21)
    - 1921-1927 (Box 21)
    - 1929 (Box 21)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 21)
    - 1937 (Box 21)
    - 1941-1943 (Box 21)
    - 1947-1952 (Box 21)
    - 1953-1958 (Box 21)
    - 1959 (Box 21)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 22)
    - 1962-1963, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - 1964-1966 (Box 22)
    - 1966-1967, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - 1968 (Box 22)
    - Executive course, 5 folders (Box 22)
    - Social Welfare Administration, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Teaching Materials
    - General (Box 22)
    - Agencies (Box 22)
    - Boards (Box 22)
    - Bureaucracy (Box 22)
    - Cases (Box 22)
    - Committees (Box 22)
    - Concepts (Box 22)
    - Employment (Box 22)
    - Evaluation (Box 22)
    - Excessive workload (Box 22)
    - Executive (Box 22)
    - Financial administration (Box 22)
    - History (Box 22)
    - Introduction (Box 22)
    - Job analysis (Box 22)
    - Leadership (Box 22)
    - Meetings (Box 22)
    - Methods of administration (Box 22)
    - Minutes and agenda (Box 22)
    - Nature of administration (Box 22)
    - Organization (Box 22)
    - Personnel-Politics (Box 22)
    - Procedures (Box 22)
    - Public relations (Box 22)
    - Race relations-Reports (Box 22)
    - Social sciences-Summary (Box 22)
    - Teams-Unions (Box 22)
    - Work plans (Box 22)
    - Writing-Yardsticks (Box 22)
  - Teaching Materials
    - General (Box 22)
    - Agencies (Box 22)
    - Boards (Box 22)
    - Bureaucracy (Box 22)
    - Cases (Box 22)
    - Committees (Box 22)
    - Concepts (Box 22)
    - Employment (Box 22)
    - Evaluation (Box 22)
    - Excessive workload (Box 22)
    - Executive (Box 22)
    - Financial administration (Box 22)
    - History (Box 22)
    - Introduction (Box 22)
    - Job analysis (Box 22)
    - Leadership (Box 22)
    - Meetings (Box 22)
    - Methods of administration (Box 22)
    - Minutes and agenda (Box 22)
    - Nature of administration (Box 22)
    - Organization (Box 22)
    - Personnel-Politics (Box 22)
    - Procedures (Box 22)
    - Public relations (Box 22)
    - Race relations-Reports (Box 22)
    - Social sciences-Summary (Box 22)
    - Teams-Unions (Box 22)
    - Work plans (Box 22)
    - Writing-Yardsticks (Box 22)
- Public Welfare
  Public Welfare is similar to the preceding three series, though much smaller. It includes course outlines, lecture notes, teaching materials, and other papers.
  - Course outlines
    - 1931,1943 (Box 23)
    - 1950,1962 (Box 23)
  - Lecture notes, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Teaching materials (Box 23)
  - Papers
    - 1926-1935 (Box 23)
    - 1936 (Box 23)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 23)
    - 1939-1948 (Box 23)
    - 1949-1958 (Box 23)
- Conscientious Objection
  The Conscientious Objection series includes detailed diaries and correspondence principally covering Dunham's incarceration during World War I. In addition, it includes an unpublished manuscript describing Dunham's experiences during this period and various pamphlets published in support of conscientious objection.
  - "Narrative of a Conscientious Objector" by Arthur Dunham (manuscript), 4 volumes (Box 23)
  - Letters from Dunham
    - 1917 (Box 23)
    - July 1918 (Box 23)
    - August 1-10, 1918 (Box 23)
    - August 11-20, 1918 (Box 23)
    - August 21-31, 1918 (Box 23)
    - September 2-10, 1918 (Box 23)
    - September 11-23, 1918 (Box 23)
    - January 1919 (Box 23)
  - Letters to Dunham
    - July-October 1918 (Box 23)
    - November 1918-January 1919 (Box 23)
  - Letters re. Dunham's incarceration November 1918-January 1919 (Box 23)
  - Telegrams re. Dunham's incarceration November 1918-January 1919 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence with Knud Lassen 1919-1923 (Box 23)
  - List of World War I Conscientious Objectors (Box 23)
  - "Diary Conscientious Objectors Camp July-September 1918" (Box 23)
  - "Diary, Guard House, Fort Riley September-November 1918" (Box 24)
  - "Diary, U.S. Disciplinary Barracks November 1918-January 1919" (Box 24)
  - "Army Casework and a Military Heretic" by Dunham (manuscript) (Box 24)
  - "Record of Trial by General Court of William Arthur Dunham" (Box 24)
  - Newspaper and magazine accounts of Fort Leavenworth strike (Box 24)
  - Pamphlets 1917-1919, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Correspondence re effort to publish "Narrative of a Conscientious Objector." (Box 24)
  - Materials re Conscientious Objection 1939-1969 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 24)
- Travel
  The Travel series covers Dunham's trip abroad in 1956 and his work in Northern Ireland in 1971. It also includes extensive field notes on community development in India.
  - Europe and Asia 1956-1957
    - Esther Dunham's journal, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Field notes, 4 folders (Box 24)
    - UNESCO Conference, Delhi November 1956 (Box 24)
    - Correspondence (Box 24)
    - Friends Meeting-Switzerland (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Northern Ireland
    - Correspondence 1970-1972 (Box 24)
    - Journal April-June 1971, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Professional materials (Box 24)
    - Community Relations Commission (Box 24)
    - Speaking material (Box 24)
    - Mimeographed material, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - "Community Development in Northern Ireland" by Hywel Griffiths (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 24)
  - Hawaii correspondence 1976 (Box 24)
- Work reports
  A smaller series - Work Reports - is dated 1953 to 1964.
  - 1953-1957, 4 folders (Box 24)
  - 1957-1964, 9 folders (Box 25)
- Social Work-Social Welfare
  Social Work-Social Welfare includes speeches and articles about these topics.
  - Biography (Box 25)
  - Profession (Box 25)
  - History and definition (Box 25)
  - Speeches and articles 1924-1953 (Box 25)
  - Speaking material, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Certification (Box 25)
- Curtis Osborn/Jane Wayland Children's Home, Phoenix, Az.
  The Curtis Osborn-Jane Wayland Children's Home series contains an extremely detailed diary compiled by Osborn describing his running of the Jane Wayland Children's Home in Phoenix, Arizona from 1947 to 1950. This project was apparently under Dunham's guidance.
  - October 1947-October 1950, 28 folders (Box 25)
  - November-December 1950, 2 folders (Box 26)
- Topical file
  Topical Files is a series maintained by Dunham consisting of both personal and collected material on subjects of interest to the Dunhams.
  - Addams, Jane (Box 26)
  - Ann Arbor-Survey of Social Welfare Program 1940 (Box 26)
  - Autographs (Box 26)
  - Bentley, Alvin (Box 26)
  - Case books 1947-1948, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - College records of Arthur and Esther Dunham (Box 26)
  - Community Welfare Councils (Box 26)
  - Community Welfare Organization history (Box 26)
  - Conference on Community Development Training, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Conflict-article (Box 26)
  - "Defining Community Organization Practice" (Box 26)
  - Dunham, Esther
    - Published material and bibliography (Box 26)
    - "The International Neighbors" (manuscript) (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous writings (Box 26)
  - Dunham, Richard (correspondence) (Box 26)
  - Dunham, Robert and Dawn (correspondence) (Box 26)
  - Encyclopedia of Social Work (Box 26)
  - Flint tornado 1953 (Box 26)
  - George Batten Advertising Company, Employment with 1913-1914 (Box 26)
  - Griffiths, Hywel (Box 26)
  - Hammarstrom, Ruth Dunham (Box 26)
  - High school records of Arthur Dunham (Box 26)
  - Intentional Communities, Fellowship of (Box 26)
  - Jewish Community Center (Box 26)
  - Letters of recommendation (Box 26)
  - Marriage of Arthur and Esther Dunham (Box 26)
  - Michigan Historical Collections (Box 26)
  - "Monroe Community Center" by Wallace Natt (manuscript) 1949 (Box 26)
  - National Association of Social Workers. Neighborhood Action Project 1966 (Box 26)
  - National Conference of Social Work Report 1940 (Box 26)
  - Northside Seniors Association (Box 26)
  - Quotations, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Race Relations, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - "Research in Social Welfare: Proposed Program for U.M.," 1954 (Box 26)
  - Retirees-University of Michigan (Box 26)
  - Retirement-speaking material (Box 26)
  - Rickart, Wesley Penn (Box 26)
  - Russell Sage Foundation Yearbook (Box 26)
  - Seminar project 1971 (Box 26)
  - Social Welfare History Archives (Box 26)
  - Social Work Vocational Bureau (Box 26)
  - Speeches-miscellaneous (Box 26)
  - Student protest 1967 (clippings) (Box 26)
  - United Nations (Box 26)
  - Welfare legislation--Michigan 1930s (Box 26)
  - Welfare mothers protest (clippings) 1968 (Box 26)
  - West Central Organization Annual Convention 1966 (Box 27)
  - Clippings (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 27)
- Unpublished manuscripts
  Within Unpublished Manuscripts, the researcher will find childhood and college writings of Dunham, his master's these on Progressive Party of 1912, a chronological run of unpublished papers, and a study entitled, "Public Relief in Three Michigan Counties."
  - Childhood writings, 14 folders (Box 27)
  - Childhood writings, 2 volumes (Box 27)
  - College writings
    - "The Eagle" (Journal), 3 folders (Box 27)
    - "Royal Interference with Parliamentary Elections" (undergraduate thesis) (Box 27)
    - "The Progressive Party of 1912" (Master's thesis) (Box 27)
  - Papers
    - 1928-1929 (Box 27)
    - 1930-1932 (Box 27)
    - 1933-1936 (Box 27)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 27)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 27)
    - 1941-1945 (Box 28)
    - 1947 (Box 28)
    - 1953-195 (Box 28)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 28)
    - 1963-1967 (Box 28)
    - 1971-1975 (Box 28)
  - "Public Relief in Three Michigan Counties" 1940, 1 volumes (Box 28)
  - "Case Problems in Community Organization and Social Welfare Administration," 1955, 2 volumes (Box 28)
- Published material
  The Published Material series begins with a "Scrapbooks of Published Material" assembled by Dunham and including most of his publications from 1916 to 1978. The arrangement is basically chronological, and each document is numbered. This subseries is preceded by an index listing material by document number, subject, and title. The subseries following the Scrapbooks contain published material not included in the scrapbooks. The series also includes published books and articles of Dunham.
  - Scrapbooks of published material
    - Introduction (Box 28)
    - Index to scrapbooks (Box 28)
    - 1916-1923 (nos. 1-6) (Box 28)
    - 1923-1925 (nos. 7-15) (Box 28)
    - 1926-1927 (nos. 16-25) (Box 28)
    - 1928-1930 (nos. 26-38) (Box 29)
    - January 1931-May 1932 (nos. 39-44) (Box 29)
    - August 1932-December 1933 (nos. 45-52) (Box 29)
    - 1934-1935 (nos. 53-63) (Box 29)
    - 1936-1937 (nos. 64-71) (Box 29)
    - 1938 (no. 72) (Box 29)
    - August-December 1938 (nos. 73-79) (Box 29)
    - January-June 1939 (nos. 80-82) (Box 29)
    - July 1939-September 1940 (nos. 83-85) (Box 29)
    - October 1940-December 1941 (nos. 86-90) (Box 29)
    - January-March 1942 (no. 91) (Box 29)
    - April 1942-December 1943 (nos. 92-98) (Box 29)
    - 1945-1948 (nos. 99-110) (Box 29)
    - 1949-1954 (nos. 111-122) (Box 29)
    - January 1955-October 1956 (nos. 123-129) (Box 29)
    - November 1956-April 1958 (nos. 131-135) (Box 29)
    - June 1958 (no. 136) (Box 29)
    - August 1958-March 1959 (nos. 137-140) (Box 29)
    - Spring 1959-October 1959 (nos. 141-145) (Box 29)
    - January 1960-April 1961 (nos. 146-148) (Box 29)
    - May 1961-April 1962 (nos. 149-154) (Box 29)
    - 1962 (no. 155) (Box 29)
    - January 1963-May 1965 (nos. 156-159) (Box 29)
    - June 1965-December 1966 (nos. 160-162) (Box 29)
    - 1967 (nos. 163-166) (Box 29)
    - 1968 (nos. 167-169) (Box 30)
    - January 1970-June 1971 (nos. 169-174) (Box 30)
    - August 1971-May 1972 (no. 175) (Box 30)
    - June 1972-December 1978 (no. 176-183) (Box 30)
  - Articles and pamphlets
    - 1924-1925 (Box 30)
    - 1928-1929 (Box 30)
    - 1930-1932 (Box 30)
    - 1933 (Box 30)
    - 1934-1937 (Box 30)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 30)
    - 1941 (Box 30)
    - 1942 (Box 30)
    - 1943-1946 (Box 30)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 30)
    - 1949, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 30)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 30)
    - 1958 (Box 30)
    - 1959 (Box 30)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 30)
    - 1962, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - 1963, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - 1964 (Box 30)
    - 1965, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - 1966 (Box 30)
    - 1968-1972 (Box 30)
    - 1973, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - 1974 (Box 30)
    - 1978 (Box 30)
  - Reports, proceedings, etc.
    - "The Juvenile Court of Lackawanna County," 1930 (Box 31)
    - "Central Registration Bureau of the Municipal Court of Philadelphia," 1930 (Box 31)
    - "Filing of Social Case Records in the Municipal Court of Philadelphia," 1930 (Box 31)
    - "Governmental Relief," 1932 (Box 31)
    - "Unemployment Relief in Pennsylvania," 1933 (Box 31)
    - "Community Organization," 1939 (Box 31)
    - "Standards Study, 1938-1940," (Box 31)
    - "The Consultation Bureau of Detroit," 1946 (Box 31)
    - "Teamwork for Community Service in New York City," 1948 (Box 31)
    - "Institute on Methods of Social Action: Proceedings," 1954 (Box 31)
    - "Role of the Board of Directors in the Social Agency of Today," 1954 (Box 31)
    - "Strengthening Our Communities Through Social Welfare," 1954 (Box 31)
    - "Social Progress Through Community Development," 1955 (Box 31)
    - "Licensing of Group Care Facilities for Children," 1960 (Box 31)
    - "Report of the Seminar on Urban Community Development," India 1965 (Box 31)
    - "The Community Organization Worker and Social Change: Workshop Proceedings," 1965 (Box 31)
    - "Types of Jobs in Community Development," 1966 (Box 31)
    - "European Workshop on Problems in Community Work Education and Training," 1971 (Box 31)
    - "Popular Participation in Development," 1971 (Box 31)
    - "Social Work with the Community," Seminar, Greece 1971 (Box 31)
  - Books
    - Philadelphia Municipal Court Survey Series, 1930, 3 volumes (Box 31)
    - The Public Assistance Worker, 1938, 1 volumes (Box 32)
    - Children in a Depression Decade, 1940, 1 volumes (Box 32)
    - Community-Welfare Organization: Principles and Practice, 1958, 1 volumes (Box 32)
    - Community Organization in Action, 1959, 1 volumes (Box 32)
    - Trends in Community Organization by Mona Heath, 1953, 1 volumes (Box 32)
    - Trends in Community Organization by Heath and Dunham, 1963, 1 volumes (Box 32)
    - The New Community Organization, 1970, 1 volumes (Box 32)
    - Dunham Genealogy by Isaac Watson Dunham, 1907, 1 volumes (Box 32)
- Photographs
  Photographs includes portraits, family photos, and photos relating to his work, including Social Service Exchanges (1920s) and community development seminars (1950s and 1960s). There are also photos of a World War I conscientious objector prison camp at Fort Douglas, Utah, and photos of an Ann Arbor Friends meeting.
  - Portraits
    - Early (Box 33)
    - Later (Box 33)
  - Arthur, Esther, and children (Box 33)
  - Ann Arbor Friends Meeting (Box 33)
  - Community Development Seminars, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Family and friends (Box 33)
  - Fort Douglas, Utah, C.O. Prison Camp 1919-1920 (Box 33)
  - Social Service Exchanges 1922-1924 (Box 33)
  - Social Welfare Exhibit, Newtonville, Massachusetts 1925 (Box 33)